<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Making Models FAIR – Updates</title><link>/blog/updates/</link><description>Recent content in Updates on Making Models FAIR</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/blog/updates/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Blog: Launching Making Models FAIR!</title><link>/blog/2023/03/15/launching-making-models-fair/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/blog/2023/03/15/launching-making-models-fair/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Imagine a world where models are available to build upon. You do not have to build from scratch and painstakingly try to figure out how published papers are getting the published results. To achieve this utopian world, models have to be findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable (FAIR). With the &amp;ldquo;Making Models FAIR&amp;rdquo; initiative, we seek to contribute to moving towards this world.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure class="card rounded p-2 td-post-card mb-4 mt-4" style="max-width: 710px">
&lt;img class="card-img-top" src="/blog/2023/03/15/launching-making-models-fair/earth-network_hudf4ff16a0e1cf0ccab58f85b36d44d0b_113023_700x250_fill_q75_catmullrom_smart1.jpg" width="700" height="250">
&lt;figcaption class="card-body px-0 pt-2 pb-0">
&lt;p class="card-text"> &lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>The initiative aims to provide a platform to learn the skills needed to make models FAIR. We provided an initial list of widely cited agent-based models, and now we can see how far we can get as a community in making them all FAIR! We expect that this initiative will be an avenue to identify potential improvements that could be made into a master list of &amp;ldquo;best practices&amp;rdquo; in making models FAIR. We also offer educational material, which will help you learn:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://comses.net/education/responsible-practices/">what FAIR is&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.comses.net/resources/standards/">how to do robust model documentation&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://comses.net/education/intro-to-git-github/">how to use GitHub&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>So, are you ready to join the community, improve your skills and knowledge, and contribute to this public good? Check out to the &lt;a href="https://tobefair.org">initiative website&lt;/a>, learn the &lt;a href="https://tobefair.org/about/">proposed process&lt;/a>, and &lt;a href="https://tobefair.org/docs/models/">find a model&lt;/a> to work on!&lt;/strong>
&lt;br>
&lt;br>
&lt;em>Many thanks to those who have contributed to the development of the content, website, and GitHub architecture that will make this community initiative possible.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>