<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Making Models FAIR – Process for Making a Model FAIR</title><link>/docs/process/</link><description>Recent content in Process for Making a Model FAIR on Making Models FAIR</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="/docs/process/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: Assess a Model's FAIR criteria</title><link>/docs/process/assessment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/process/assessment/</guid><description>
&lt;p>Each model has been initially assessed against the five FAIR criteria based on the information provided in the associated publication (see each model&amp;rsquo;s assessment on the &lt;a href="/docs/models/">Models&lt;/a> page). In the process of making the model FAIR, additional information may need to be brought in beyond what was only provided in the publication. The accompanying GitHub repository for each model publication will serve to keep the score on the improvements of the FAIR components of the published model.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Each of the five FAIR criteria are outlined below, with their associated &amp;ldquo;scoring&amp;rdquo; options.
For the sake of this initiative, &lt;strong>a model would be considered FAIR once it achieves the bolded option for each criterion.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-1__-available-code">&lt;strong>Criterion 1.&lt;/strong> Available code&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Is the model code available in a publicly accessible repository?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Yes&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>A link might be provided in a publication; but if the link is not working, we score it a No in the initial scoring.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-2__-license">&lt;strong>Criterion 2.&lt;/strong> License&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Does the model have a license?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Yes&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Typically, license information is provided in the publicly accessible repository.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-3__-doi">&lt;strong>Criterion 3.&lt;/strong> DOI&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Does the model code repository have a DOI?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Yes&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>If the model code is publicly available, does the location have a DOI?&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-4__-model-documentation">&lt;strong>Criterion 4.&lt;/strong> Model Documentation&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Does the model has detailed documentation?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We provide a letter grade based on a casual reading of the model publication. Whether the model documentation is sufficient to understand the details of the model can only be found out in an actual replication exercise.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>A - Excellent.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Documentation provides clear rational for the purpose of the model and the assumptions behind the model formulation. There is a clear description of the processes, ideally with a visual representation (flow chart). All the variables and parameters of the model are clearly defined (including units and source of estimation for the parameters). The source of data files are provided. The details of the mechanism of the model are described by mathematical equations or pseudo code.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>B - Good.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Compared to an A. there are some details missing like sources of data to define parameter values, the units, a clear description of the order in which processes are executed, etc. For small-scale theoretical models (without data) a detailed narrative based on logical statements could be sufficient for replication of the model.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>C - Satisfactory.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Compared with B. Model (beyond a small theoretical model) lacks equations and pseudocode to describe the details of the model.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>D - Less than Satisfactory.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Compared with C. Model does not defined all variables and parameters. Values of parameters are missing. Details of the processes of the model is missing. It might not be sufficient to replicate the model.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>E - Unsatisfactory.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Compared to D. Lack of sufficient information to understand the basic structure of the model.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-5__-clean-model-code">&lt;strong>Criterion 5.&lt;/strong> Clean Model Code&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Is the model code cleaned up and well commented?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We provide a letter grade based on a causal evaluation of the provided code (if code was provided). This criterion is not able to be graded at all until there is available code.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A - Excellent.&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Defines variables and parameters (including units). Describes and explains each procedure and key processes of the model. Mentions version number and authors of the code. No outcommented lines of code to test the model, and no informal comments among authors.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>B - Good.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Compared to A. Missing some details such as units, has not defined all variables and parameters, did not mention authors of the code.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>C - Satisfactory.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Compared to B. Becomes a bit messy, includes unnecessary lines of test code and informal comments among authors.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>D - Less than Satisfactory.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Compared to C. Does not define variables and parameters, does not provide description of procedures. One may understand the workings of the code, but it will take a lot of effort.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>E - Unsatisfactory.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Code dump. No relevant comments, many outcommented lines of code, unclear what code is actually used for the model.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Docs: How to Make A Model FAIR</title><link>/docs/process/how-to/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/process/how-to/</guid><description>
&lt;p>For each of the five FAIR criteria considered, we provide guidance on how to meet those criteria when they are absent or inadequate. These guidelines will be continually updated based on experience, reflection, and learning fostered by this initiative.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Please share your experiences or reflections on the &lt;a href="https://github.com/make-models-fair/coordination/discussions">discussion page&lt;/a> of our coordination repository so that we can all benefit from them! Additionally, you should create new issues in the associated GitHub repository for the model you are working on, to document the actions you are taking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="__potential-problems--solutions__-br-by-criterion">&lt;strong>Potential Problems &amp;amp; Solutions&lt;/strong> &lt;br> (by criterion)&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-1__-available-code">&lt;strong>Criterion 1.&lt;/strong> Available code&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Problem&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Solution&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Code is not available in a publicly accessible repository.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Contact the authors and inquire about the availability of the original code of the model.&lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;em>If they provide the code:&lt;/em> Ask whether it is OK to make the code publicly available. &lt;br>&lt;br> &lt;em>If the code is not findable (or authors do not want to make their code publicly available):&lt;/em> Try to replicate the code from the model description of the publication (using the GitHub repository associated with this model).&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>The basic results published in the publication are not replicable.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>While replication is not required to score the first criterion as &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; according to this initiative&amp;rsquo;s assessment guidance, it does indicate that there may be issues with the code that would inhibit reproducibility. This may be an issue with differences in program or package versions, missing pieces of the code, or bugs in the software.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;hr>
&lt;br>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-2__-license">&lt;strong>Criterion 2.&lt;/strong> License&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Problem&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Solution&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>The model code has no license.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Give it an appropriate community based license. If you received the code from the authors, consult with them on the selection of the license.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;hr>
&lt;br>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-3__-doi">&lt;strong>Criterion 3.&lt;/strong> DOI&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Problem&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Solution&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>The model code repository has no DOI.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Archive the model code in an archive that provides a DOI, such as &lt;a href="https://zenodo.org">Zenodo&lt;/a> or &lt;a href="https://comses.net">CoMSES Net&lt;/a>. &lt;br> * &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://docs.github.com/en/repositories/archiving-a-github-repository/referencing-and-citing-content">See here&lt;/a> for more information on making code citable by linking GitHub with Zenodo.&lt;/em> &lt;br> * &lt;em>Learn how to &lt;a href="https://www.comses.net/codebases/add/">archive&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://www.comses.net/reviews/">submit your model for peer review&lt;/a> on CoMSES Net.&lt;/em>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;hr>
&lt;br>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-4__-model-documentation">&lt;strong>Criterion 4.&lt;/strong> Model Documentation&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Problem&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Solution&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Documentation quality can be improved.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Improve the model description. For example, describe the purpose of the model, add visual flow diagrams, equations, and pseudo code, describe submodels. Provide sources of datasets used by the model. In principle the model should be capable of being replicated based on just the model documentation.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;hr>
&lt;br>
&lt;h4 id="__criterion-5__-clean-model-code">&lt;strong>Criterion 5.&lt;/strong> Clean Model Code&lt;/h4>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>Problem&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Solution&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>Code is not sufficiently cleaned up and commented.&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Clean up the code by removing commented out or unused (&amp;ldquo;dead&amp;rdquo;) code, refactoring the code to provide clear and meaningful variable names, adding comments that describe the intent, purpose, and any assumptions in all methods / functions / procedures / classes.&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;hr></description></item></channel></rss>